Harris Graphics Company Records 1989.0090
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Harris Graphics Company Records
undated, 1879-1979
1989.0090
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
14.0 Linear feet
The Harris Graphics Company Records consists of the administrative and financial records of the Harris Graphics Company and C.B. Cottrell & Sons, a printing press manufacturer bought out by Harris Graphics in the early 1980s.
History
The Cottrell Company was founded in 1855 by Calvert B. Cottrell and Nathan Babcock in Westerly, Rhode Island, to manufacture general machinery. In addition to cotton and woodworking machinery the company produced printing presses. By 1868, the Cottrell Company was producing printing presses exclusively, and Calvert Cottrell began to develop improvements to the form. Adapting his presses to new technology, Cottrell produced steam powered presses that improved the overall quality and speed of printing. The partnership between Cottrell and Babcock ended in 1880 when Babcock retired from the company.
Renamed C. B. Cottrell & Sons, Calvert brought his sons into the business and continued to develop new printing technologies to set his presses apart. One of Calvert's greatest technological innovations was the Cottrell Black Perfecting Web Press, which printed on both sides of a roll of paper without smudging the ink on either side. Introduced in 1890, it had a large impact on printing, and the printing of magazines in particular.
The company continued to grow and introduce innovative printing technologies. During World War II, C. B. Cottrell & Sons partnered with the Harris-Seybold Company of Cleveland to produce print materials for the U.S. Army. In 1953, Cottrell & Sons, by then a leader in supplying high-speed web letterpresses for mass ciculation magazines, was acquired by the Harris-Seybold Company. The Westerly plant (actually located in Pawcatuck, Connecticut) then manufactured four-color web offset presses. The company, still called C. B. Cottrell & and Sons, was sold again in the early 1980s to the Harris Graphics Group. The Harris Graphics Group continued to produce press machinery until 1989 when the factory was shut down due to a drop in the demand for new printing equipment.
Scope and Contents
Spanning the years 1879 to 1979, the collection contains administrative and financial records, correspondence, notes, photographs, and artwork focusing mainly on C. B. Cottrell & Sons, which was later acquired by the Harris Graphics Company. These records include surveys, inventories, patent assignments for various printing related technologies, pamphlets for employees, and other materials tracking the operation of the company before C. B. Cottrell & Sons was acquired by Harris Graphics. Records of the early Cottrell Company and Harris Graphics are less prevalent in the collection.
Also included in the collection are approx. 150 glass plate negatives, undated but likely early 1900s, of printing presses and machinery manufactured by C. B. Cottrell & Sons.
Access
The collection is open and available for research. The glass plate negatives may be handled only under the supervision of reference desk staff.
Provenance and Acquisition
The collection was donated in 1989 by Harris Graphics Company.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to Connecticut businesses. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the Reading Room desk.
C.B. Cottrell & Sons, Inc.; Harris Graphics Company.; Artwork.; Correspondence.; Financial Records.; Glass negatives.; Legal documents.; Notes.; Pamphlets.; Pawcatuck [Conn.]; Photographs.; Printing presses.; Westerly [R.I.]
- Series I: Inventory, undated, circa 1890-circa 1985
  - Administrative Records (Color Presses), 1940 (Box 1)
    Scope and Content Note
    [Subjects include: inventory lists, C.B. Cottrell and Sons, Claybourn Corp.]
  - Administrative records, notes (Color Presses), 1930-1949 (Box 2)
  - Administrative records (Color Presses), 1946-1954 (Box 3)
    [Subjects include: inventory lists, plate cylinders, C.B. Cottrell and Sons, Claybourn Corp.]
  - Notes, administrative records, correspondence (Color Presses), 1944 (Box 4)
  - Financial records, administrative records, notes (Color Presses), 1946-1965 (Box 5)
    [Subjects include: surveys, data, funds, training, waste reduction, job instruction, fundamentals of management, techniques of supervision, Fort Worth, Texas sales department, Y.M.C.A. Sunday Morning Activities, Engineering department, M.D.T.A. training, Connecticut State Department of Education, Attendance Control – Union Employees, C. B. Cottrell and Sons, Claybourn Corp., Field Surveys, Security Plant, Wages and Salaries (Pfizer) Survey.]
  - Administrative records, photographs, 1965-1970 (Box 7)
    [Subjects include: recommendations, opinion surveys, Stonington Security Agency, the Cottrell Company: processes and procedures, Thames Valley Technical College Council, Surveys, Servomation Corporation, Martin Wright and Associates, Cottrell Company policies and procedures.]
  - Administrative records, fliers, artwork, correspondence, notes, 1881-1910 (Box 8)
    [Subjects include: pamphlets, assignment of patents, Cottrell & Sons, assignment of improvement in Steam pumps, C.A. Stillman, George P. Fenner, agreements, Campbell Printing Press, Paper folding machine, sketches, Babcock Printing Press, license, Empire Machine Co., Sundry notes, deposits, Empire Machine Co., Cottrell and Babcock, Bank Notes.]
  - Notes, administrative records, financial records, lists, 1879-1913 (Box 9)
    [Subjects include: Cottrell & Sons, John Dunn Executor of the Estate of Charles Annand, New England Lines Industrial Bureau, statements, briefs, claims, Babcock & Wilcox Boiler, Pendleton & Co., E. Gaillard, bills, agreements, receipts, water analysis, Washington National Bank, C.B. Cottrell and Sons Co., C.B. Cottrell vs. Nathan Babcock.]
  - Administrative records, financial records, 1959-1966 (Box 10)
    [Subjects include: job descriptions, Fort Worth, Texas, Engineering, controller, budget supervisors, internal auditor, paymaster, secretary and manager of contracts, manager of customer financing, child development engineer, chief electrical engineer, erecting inspector, project engineer, Cottrell Co. management manual.]
  - Administrative records, 1963-1979 (Box 11)
    [Subjects include: personnel, job openings, managers, respresentatives, Fort Worth, Texas.]
  - Glass plate negatives of C.B. Cottrell & Sons printing presses and machinery, undated (Box 12)
  - Glass plate negatives of C.B. Cottrell & Sons printing presses and machinery, undated (Box 13)
  - Glass plate negatives of C.B. Cottrell & Sons printing presses and machinery, undated (Box 14)